<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>普癌新声</title>
<link>https://chenq.site/publications/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://chenq.site/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>一个公共卫生医师的个人网站</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.14</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Mar 20222 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>2017年河南省肝癌流行现状及2010—2017年趋势分析</title>
  <dc:creator>刘茵,陈琼,张璐瑶,郭兰伟,徐慧芳,康瑞华,郑黎阳,王潇杨,王红,刘曙正,孙喜斌,张韶凯</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-03-15-liver-cancer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="目的" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="目的">[目的]</h2>
<p>分析河南省肝癌2017年发病、死亡现状及2010—2017年发病、死亡变化趋势。</p>
</section>
<section id="方法" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="方法">[方法]</h2>
<p>利用河南省肿瘤登记处上报的、质控合格的肝癌发病与死亡资料，结合全省户籍人口数据，估算2017年分城乡、性别、年龄组别发病与死亡率、构成比、中标率、世标率和累积率（0～74岁），分析2010—2017年河南省肝癌中标发病（死亡）率的年均变化百分比（AAPC）及其95%置信区间（CI）。[结果] 2017年河南省肝癌新发病例数估计为31 508例，死亡病例数估计为26 732例。2017年河南省肝癌发病率为29.10/10万，中标率为21.62/10万，世标率为21.45/10万，累积率（0～74岁）为2.45%。2017年河南省肝癌死亡率为24.69/10万，中标率为17.77/10万，世标率为17.88/10万，累积率（0～74岁）为2.00%。中标发病率和死亡率均呈现农村高于城市地区、男性高于女性的特点。肝癌年龄别发病率和死亡率均随年龄增加而上升，在85+岁达到峰值。2010—2017年，河南省肝癌中标发病（死亡）率整体均呈平稳趋势，城市地区中标发病率呈显著下降趋势（AAPC=-2.3%,95%CI:-4.3%～-0.1%）。</p>
</section>
<section id="结论" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结论">[结论]</h2>
<p>河南省肝癌疾病负担严重，整体发病率与死亡率均未出现明显下降趋势，应继续加强肝癌防控，对重点人群实施干预，推进筛查与早诊早治等工作。</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>中文论文</category>
  <category>共同作者</category>
  <category>肿瘤登记</category>
  <category>中国肿瘤</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-03-15-liver-cancer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 20222 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Development and Validation of a Noninvasive Risk Score Model for Liver Cirrhosis in At-Risk Alcohol Drinkers Without HBV/HCV Infection</title>
  <dc:creator>Yin Liu, Lan-Wei Guo, Hui-Fang Xu, Rui-Hua Kang, Li-Yang Zheng, Lu-Yao Zhang, &lt;strong&gt;Qiong Chen&lt;/strong&gt;, Xi-Bin Sun, You-Lin Qiao, Shao-Kai Zhang</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-risk-score-model.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>At-risk alcohol consumption is the established most important risk factor for cirrhosis in people without HBV/HCV infection. We aimed to develop and validate a simple and non-invasive tool for triaging cirrhosis risk in at-risk alcohol drinkers without HBV/HCV infection. A large-sample size, cross-sectional study within the framework of a population-based Cancer Screening Program in Urban China (CanSPUC) was conducted. Data on the liver cancer screening in Henan province, China were used. At-risk alcohol drinkers were those who currently drink one or more alcohol units per week for at least six months. A total of 6,581 eligible participants enrolled from October 1, 2013 to December 31, 2016 were included into the derivation dataset, and 2,096 eligible participants enrolled from January 1, 2017 to October 31, 2018 were included into the external validation dataset, respectively. Using the derivation dataset, a 20-point scale risk score model was developed, based on sex, education background, dietary intake of vegetables, dietary intake of roughage, smoking index, length of secondhand smoke exposure, history of fatty liver, history of diabetes, and first-degree family history of liver cancer. The model showed excellent discrimination (AUC = 0.787; 95% CI, 0.7603-0.812) and calibration (Hosmer-Lemeshow test: P = 0.123) in the derivation dataset and an optimal cut-off value of 12 yield sensitivity of 61.3%, specificity of 82.7%. The model also had achieved similar performance in the external validation dataset. In conclusion, this model can be a practical tool to identify and triage population at high risk of cirrhosis in at-risk alcohol drinkers without HBV/HCV infection.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>英文论文</category>
  <category>共同作者</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-risk-score-model.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Evaluation of a Low-Dose Computed Tomography Lung Cancer Screening Program in Henan, China</title>
  <dc:creator>Lan-Wei Guo, &lt;strong&gt;Qiong Chen&lt;/strong&gt;, Yin-Chen Shen, Qing-Cheng Meng, Li-Yang Zheng, Yue Wu, Xiao-Qin Cao, Hui-Fang Xu, Shu-Zheng Liu, Xi-Bin Sun, You-Lin Qiao, Shao-Kai Zhang</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2020-LDCT-screening-effect.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="importance" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="importance">Importance</h2>
<p>Lung cancer screening has been widely implemented in Europe and the US. However, there is little evidence on participation and diagnostic yields in population-based lung cancer screening in China.</p>
</section>
<section id="objective" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="objective">Objective</h2>
<p>To assess the participation rate and detection rate of lung cancer in a population-based screening program and the factors associated with participation.</p>
</section>
<section id="design-setting-and-participants" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="design-setting-and-participants">Design, setting, and participants</h2>
<p>This cross-sectional study used data from the Cancer Screening Program in Urban China from October 2013 to October 2019, with follow-up until March 10, 2020. The program is conducted at centers in 8 cities in Henan Province, China. Eligible participants were aged 40 to 74 and were evaluated for a high risk for lung cancer using an established risk score system.</p>
</section>
<section id="main-outcomes-and-measures" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="main-outcomes-and-measures">Main outcomes and measures</h2>
<p>Overall and group-specific participation rates by common factors, such as age, sex, and educational level, were calculated. Differences in participation rates between those groups were compared. The diagnostic yield of both screening and nonscreening groups was calculated.</p>
</section>
<section id="results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results">Results</h2>
<p>The study recruited 282 377 eligible participants and included 55 428 with high risk for lung cancer; the mean (SD) age was 55.3 (8.1) years, and 34 966 participants (63.1%) were men. A total of 22 260 participants underwent LDCT (participation rate, 40.16%; 95% CI, 39.82%-40.50%). The multivariable logistic regression model showed that female sex (odds ratio [OR], 1.64; 95% CI, 1.52-1.78), former smoking (OR, 1.26; 95% CI, 1.13-1.41), lack of physical activity (OR, 1.19; 95% CI, 1.14-1.24), family history of lung cancer (OR, 1.73; 95% CI, 1.66-1.79), and 7 other factors were associated with increased participation of LDCT screening. Overall, at 6-year follow-up, 78 participants in the screening group (0.35%; 95% CI, 0.29%-0.42%) and 125 in the nonscreening group (0.38%; 95% CI, 0.33%-0.44%) had lung cancer detected, which resulted in an odds ratio of 0.93 (95% CI, 0.70-1.23; P = .61).</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusions-and-relevance" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusions-and-relevance">Conclusions and relevance</h2>
<p>The low participations rate in the program studied suggests that an improved strategy is needed. These findings may provide useful information for designing effective population-based lung cancer screening strategies in the future.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>英文论文</category>
  <category>共同作者</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2020-LDCT-screening-effect.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>胃癌内镜筛查对统计治愈比例的影响</title>
  <dc:creator>&lt;strong&gt;陈琼&lt;/strong&gt;，李变云，刘曙正，徐慧芳，于亮，郭兰伟，张璐瑶，刘茵，王潇杨，孙喜斌，张韶凯</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-11-03-screening-cure/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="cell" data-hash="index_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-1_b9fb713eab5504a9a25eb2a72ef19b1c">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<p><img src="https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-11-03-screening-cure/preview.jpg" class="img-fluid" width="863"></p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="目的" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="目的">目的</h2>
<p>评估胃癌统计治愈率现状及其与胃癌内镜筛查之间的关系。</p>
</section>
<section id="方法" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="方法">方法</h2>
<p>提取林州市以人群为基础的肿瘤登记数据库中ICD10为C16.0~C16.9范围的胃癌病例数据，通过链接胃癌人群筛查数据库与肿瘤登记数据库以获取患者是否参加筛查状态，利用混合统计治愈模型建模并估计统计治愈比例及相对生存率，计算OR值以及95%可信区间以评估胃癌内镜筛查和统计治愈之间的关系。</p>
</section>
<section id="结果" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结果">结果</h2>
<p>曾参加内镜筛查和从未参加内镜筛查胃癌患者的统计治愈比例分别为75.51% (95%CI: 69.18% ~ 81.85%)和31.69% (95% CI: 30.30% ~ 33.07%)，估计治愈比例两者差值为38.76% (32.35% ~ 45.00%)。参加内镜筛查患者与未参加筛查患者相比，受益于统计治愈的比值比为5.84 (95%CI: 4.10 ~ 8.31)，参加内镜筛查患者收益于贲门胃统计治愈（OR: 6.10，95CI: 3.96 ~ 9.39）要高于非贲门胃(OR: 5.34，95CI: 2.54 ~ 11.23)。</p>
</section>
<section id="结论" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结论">结论</h2>
<p>参加胃癌内窥镜筛查可以提高胃癌患者统计治愈比例。</p>
<p><strong>【关键词】</strong> 胃癌；内镜筛查；统计治愈；治愈比例</p>
<p><a href="https://chenq.site/papers/cure.pdf">点击这里阅读全文</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>中文论文</category>
  <category>第一作者</category>
  <category>治愈比例</category>
  <category>中国肿瘤</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-11-03-screening-cure/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>以人群为基础的肿瘤登记建设规范</title>
  <dc:creator>张韶凯，&lt;strong&gt;陈琼&lt;/strong&gt;，张璐瑶，刘茵，徐慧芳，王潇杨，王红，康瑞华，郭兰伟，郑黎阳，刘曙正，孙喜斌</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-10-23-guideline/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="cell" data-hash="index_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-1_70afd2ed753d959e59f860d263f8d2af">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-10-23-guideline/flowchart.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="895"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">肿瘤登记数据上报流程图</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>为规范肿瘤登记工作的开展，提升肿瘤登记数据质量，进一步推动肿瘤登记工作的进程，以国际上肿瘤登记现状和趋势为依据，结合河南省肿瘤登记工作经验及现状，并参考专家意见，制定了以人群为基础的肿瘤登记工作规范。结果显示，建立以人群为基础的肿瘤登记处是开展肿瘤登记工作的基础，省卫生健康行政部门和中医药管理部门负责建立健全本辖区肿瘤登记制度，组织、协调、监督和管理本辖区肿瘤登记工作，指定省级癌症中心为省级肿瘤登记中心，承担全省肿瘤登记工作。市、县级卫生行政部门和中医药行政部门组织、协调、监督和管理本辖区的肿瘤登记工作。选择登记覆盖区域内的户籍人群作为肿瘤登记的目标人群，采用被动和主动收集相结合的方法，收集目标人群中所有恶性肿瘤、原位癌等的发病、死亡和生存信息，以及相关人口学统计资料信息，并开展随访工作。从可比性、完整性、有效性和时效性4个方面对肿瘤登记数据的质量进行评估。提示，健全的肿瘤登记工作规范是肿瘤登记工作质量的坚实保障。在肿瘤登记处迅速增加的背景下，依据肿瘤登记工作规范开展肿瘤登记工作，对于提高肿瘤登记数据的质量至关重要，从而为肿瘤防控提供真实可靠的基础数据。</p>
<p>【关键词】 肿瘤登记; 肿瘤监测; 工作规范; 肿瘤防控;</p>
<p><a href="https://chenq.site/papers/guideline.pdf">点击阅读全文</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>中文论文</category>
  <category>共同作者</category>
  <category>肿瘤登记</category>
  <category>社区医学杂志</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-10-23-guideline/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2010-2014年河南省儿童和青少年恶性肿瘤生存分析</title>
  <dc:creator>&lt;strong&gt;陈琼&lt;/strong&gt;，张明霞，郭兰伟，王红，徐慧芳，刘茵，王潇杨，康瑞华，郑黎阳，刘曙正，孙喜斌，张韶凯</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-10-22-childhood-cancer-survival/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="目的" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="目的">目的</h2>
<p>了解河南省2010—2014年儿童和青少年恶性肿瘤患者的生存情况及其特征。</p>
</section>
<section id="方法" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="方法">方法</h2>
<p>提取河南省肿瘤登记数据库中年龄为0～19岁、诊断日期为2010年1月1日至2014年12月31日期间的所有恶性肿瘤患者数据，采用被动和主动随访方法对所有患者进行随访，按照国际儿童癌症分类第3版的分类标准对肿瘤类型进行重新分类，利用完全队列法估计相对生存率以评估儿童和青少年肿瘤生存情况。</p>
</section>
<section id="结果" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结果">结果</h2>
<p>河南省2010—2014年0～14岁儿童恶性肿瘤患者5年生存率为44.4%（95%CI:41.7%～47.1%）,15～19岁青少年恶性肿瘤患者5年生存率为52.2%（95%CI:47.7%～56.5%）。城市地区儿童和青少年恶性肿瘤5年生存率（54.6%,95%CI:48.8%～60.1%）均高于农村地区（45.0%,95%CI:42.4%～47.5%），这种城乡差异在不同性别、年龄段以及肿瘤分类的分析中均可以观察到。2013—2014年诊断的儿童和青少年恶性肿瘤的5年生存率（50.5%,95%CI:47.2%～53.7%）高于2010—2012年（42.4%,95%CI:39.1%～45.6%）。从儿童和青少年的主要肿瘤类型来看，白血病、中枢神经系统肿瘤以及骨肿瘤的5年生存率分别为40.1%（95%CI:36.6%～43.5%）、35.2%（29.9%～40.6%）和58.7%（49.2%～67.1%）。</p>
</section>
<section id="结论" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结论">结论</h2>
<p>河南省儿童和青少年恶性肿瘤的生存率与全国平均水平以及发达国家水平存在较大差距，需加强其综合防控措施以降低死亡率、提高生存率。</p>
<p>【关键词】儿童和青少年; 恶性肿瘤; 生存; 河南</p>
<p><a href="https://chenq.site/papers/childhood.pdf">点击这里阅读全文</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>中文论文</category>
  <category>第一作者</category>
  <category>肿瘤登记</category>
  <category>中国肿瘤</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-10-22-childhood-cancer-survival/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Incidence and mortality of gastric cancer in 2018 and their trends from 2010 to 2018 in Henan Province, China: results from a provincial population-based cancer registry</title>
  <dc:creator>&lt;strong&gt; Qiong Chen&lt;/strong&gt;,, Cheng C, Liu Y, Guo L, Xu H, Wang H, Wang X, Zhang L, Zhang S, Han B</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-10-14-gastric-cancer-incidence/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="background" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="background">Background</h2>
<p>Endoscopic screening program was carried out in Henan Province, China to reduce the large gastric cancer burden, and its effect evidence is insufficient. Knowledge on current status and time-trend of gastric cancer is need for policy makers to optimize the strategy of gastric cancer control.</p>
</section>
<section id="methods" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="methods">Methods</h2>
<p>Gastric cancer data were pooled from registries in the Henan Cancer Registration System which may reflect the whole province cancer incidence and mortality. The pooled registration data, stratified by area (urban/rural), gender, and age groups, was combined with the provincial population data to estimate the incidence and mortality of gastric cancer in Henan Province. The Segi’s world standard population was applied to calculate the age-standardized rate. Joinpoint regression was used to analyze the time-trend in the incidence and mortality.</p>
</section>
<section id="results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results">Results</h2>
<p>Gastric cancer was diagnosed in 33,971 patients in 2018, ranking second among all cancers. The crude incidence and age-standardized incidence rate (ASIRW) per 100,000 population were 31.15 and 23.05, respectively. In 2018, there were an estimated 25,921 gastric cancer-related deaths, ranking second among all cancer-related deaths. The crude mortality rate and age-standardized mortality rate by world standard population (ASMRW) were respectively 23.77 and 16.80 per 100,000 population. Gender and geographical differences were observed. Notably, the ASIRW and ASMRW were higher in males than females and higher in rural areas than urban areas. For ASIRW and ASMRW, the male to female ratio was 2.50 and 2.71, respectively, and the rural to urban ratio was 1.23 and 1.24, respectively. Declines in the incidence [average annual percent change (AAPC): −3.9%, P=0.001] and mortality (AAPC: −3.1%, P=0.004) of gastric cancer were observed in rural areas due to declines in the incidence and mortality among residents aged 40–69 years. The overall trend of ASIRW and ASMRW were observed to decline with AAPCs of −3.5% (P=0.003) and −2.8% (P=0.007), respectively.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>Gastric cancer incidence and mortality decreased in Henan Province, China, from 2010 to 2018, which may due to the implementation of endoscopic screening for gastric cancer in rural areas. The disease burden, however, remains high, and screening strategies and measures to reduce it should be strengthened.</p>
<p><strong>[Keywords]</strong> Gastric cancer; incidence; mortality; trend; cancer registry.</p>
</section>
<section id="figures-in-this-article" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="figures-in-this-article">Figures in this article</h2>
<div class="cell" data-hash="index_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-1_fc966ccf5b945ee32bb92c059268a469">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-10-14-gastric-cancer-incidence/images/Figure1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="1622"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Distribution of Cancer Registries in Henan Province, China that included in analysis.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell" data-hash="index_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-2_ad38e830b418e73bf79d1570def8971e">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-10-14-gastric-cancer-incidence/images/Figure2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="1045"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Cancer registration data quality control workflow.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell" data-hash="index_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-3_b672960879990f0ec7d672441992cf55">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-10-14-gastric-cancer-incidence/images/Figure3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="1350"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Age specific gastric cancer cases and incidence.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell" data-hash="index_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-4_939286f0175779ccdfa9be251df10a8c">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-10-14-gastric-cancer-incidence/images/Figure4.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="1350"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Age specific gastric cancer deaths and mortality.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell" data-hash="index_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-5_8a8141269fce05b107df7d1e48f79f93">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-10-14-gastric-cancer-incidence/images/Figure5.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="1200"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Changing trend of gastric cancer incidence and mortality in Henan Provice from 2010 to 2018.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="how-to-cite-this-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-cite-this-paper">How to Cite this paper</h2>
<p>Cite this article as: Chen Q, Cheng C, Liu Y, Guo L, Xu H, Wang H, Wang X, Zhang L, Zhang S, Han B. Incidence and mortality of gastric cancer in 2018 and their trends from 2010 to 2018 in Henan Province, China: results from a provincial population-based cancer registry. Ann Transl Med 2022;10(18):1012. doi: 10.21037/atm-22-4100.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>英文论文</category>
  <category>第一作者</category>
  <category>肿瘤登记</category>
  <category>Ann Transl Med</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-10-14-gastric-cancer-incidence/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A cluster randomized controlled trial to evaluate the efficacy of esophageal and gastric cancer screening in mortality reduction in a non-high-incidence area: methodology and initial results</title>
  <dc:creator>Xiao-Yang Wang, Shu-Zheng Liu, Hui-Fang Xu, Yin Liu, Hong Wang, Rui-Hua Kang, &lt;strong&gt;Qiong Chen&lt;/strong&gt;, Lu-Yao Zhang, Lan-Wei Guo, Li-Yang Zheng, Chun-Ya Liu, Yi-Xian Wang, Yi-Ping Jing, You-Lin Qiao, Bin-Bin Han, Shao-Kai Zhang</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-rct-esophageal-gastric-cancer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="background" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="background">Background:</h2>
<p>A cluster randomized controlled trial of endoscopy-based screening for esophageal cancer (EC) and gastric cancer (GC) was conducted to evaluate the efficacy and feasibility of this strategy in a non-high-incidence rural area of China. The trial design and baseline findings are presented here.</p>
</section>
<section id="methods" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="methods">Methods:</h2>
<p>A total of 33 eligible villages in Luoshan County in Henan Province were assigned randomly to the intervention or control group in a 1:1 ratio by a computer-generated randomization list. Local residents aged 40 to 69 years were enrolled from the villages. Participants in the intervention group were risk-stratified with a questionnaire, and high-risk individuals were subsequently screened by endoscopy. The primary outcomes were EC and GC mortality. The secondary outcomes comprised the detection rate, stage distribution, and the treatment rate. In this study, baseline characteristics were assessed by a questionnaire. Multivariate logistic regression analysis was performed to explore factors associated with endoscopy compliance.</p>
</section>
<section id="results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results">Results:</h2>
<p>Trial recruitment was completed in 2017, and ultimately, there were 12,475 and 11,442 participants allocated to the intervention (17 clusters) and the control group (16 clusters), respectively. We included 23,653 participants in the analysis, with 12,402 in the intervention group and 11,251 in the control group. A total of 6,286 (50.7%) participants in the intervention group were estimated as high-risk individuals, and 2,719 (43.3%) underwent endoscopy. Multivariate logistic regression analysis demonstrated that some factors including age, gender, education, personality and mental health, and upper gastrointestinal diseases or symptoms might affect endoscopy compliance. The detection rates for positive cases of EC and GC were 0.22% and 0.55%, respectively. The rates for esophageal and gastric precancerous lesions were 0.70% and 2.35%, respectively. The early detection rates for EC and GC were 50.0% and 33.3%, respectively. Additionally, the overall treatment rate for positive cases was 90.0%.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusions">Conclusions:</h2>
<p>The diagnostic yield of endoscopy-based screening for EC and GC was relatively low in a non-high-incidence rural area. The study may offer clues for the improvement of endoscopy compliance and the optimization of screening strategies for upper gastrointestinal cancer in non-high-incidence areas.</p>
<p>Trial registration: Chinese Clinical Trial Registry ChiCTR-EOR-16008577.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords:</strong> Upper gastrointestinal cancer; detection rate; endoscopy compliance; esophageal cancer (EC); gastric cancer (GC).</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>英文论文</category>
  <category>共同作者</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-rct-esophageal-gastric-cancer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Incidence and mortality of lung cancer in 2018 and the temporal trends from 2010 to 2018 in Henan province, China: a population-based registry study</title>
  <dc:creator>Yin Liu, &lt;strong&gt;Qiong Chen&lt;/strong&gt;, Lan-Wei Guo, Hui-Fang Xu, Xiao-Yang Wang, Rui-Hua Kang, Lu-Yao Zhang, Hong Wang, Bin-Bin Han, Shao-Kai Zhang</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-lung-cancer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="background" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="background">Background</h2>
<p>The disease burden of lung cancer is high in Henan province, China, it is out of the utmost significance to figure the current epidemic status and temporal trend of lung cancer for effective prevention and control.</p>
</section>
<section id="methods" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="methods">Methods</h2>
<p>The qualified data was obtained from the Henan Provincial Central Cancer Registry of China, covering 30.51% of the whole population. Incidence, mortality, proportions, and cumulative rates (among patients aged 0-74 years old) of lung cancer by areas, sex and age groups were estimated. The world Segi’s standard population was applied to calculate the age-standardized rate. Joinpoint regression was used to calculate annual percentage change (APC) and average annual percentage change (AAPC) to evaluate temporal trends from 2010 to 2018.</p>
</section>
<section id="results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results">Results</h2>
<p>In 2018, there were about 55,344 new cases of lung cancer in Henan province, with the crude incidence of 50.75/100,000, the age-standardized incidence rate by world standard (Segi’s) population (ASIRW) of 37.14/100,000, and the cumulative rate of 4.57%. About 41,782 people died from lung cancer in 2018, with the crude mortality rate of 38.31/100,000, the age-standardized mortality rate by world standard (Segi’s) population (ASMRW) of 27.09/100,000, and the cumulative rate of 3.22%. The age-specific incidence and mortality of lung cancer increased gradually as age increased and reached the peak at the age of 85+ years. The overall ASIRW (AAPC =0.3, P=0.531) and ASMRW (AAPC =-0.2, P=0.687) remained stable from 2010 to 2018, but decreased in urban areas from 2014 to 2018 (APC for ASIRW =-4.7, P=0.023; APC for ASMRW =-5.3, P=0.012). From 2010 to 2018, the incidence rate increased in the rural population aged 75+ years old (AAPC =4.2, P=0.023).</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>The incidence and mortality rates of lung cancer significantly decreased in urban areas partly due to the Cancer Screening Program in Urban China. Nonetheless, the disease burden remains high, especially in males and elderly population. Comprehensive prevention and control programs, such as smoking cessation intervention, screening, early diagnosis and early treatment programs, need to be implemented to reduce the burden of lung cancer.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords</strong>: Lung cancer; incidence; mortality; trend.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>英文论文</category>
  <category>共同作者</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-lung-cancer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2017年河南省恶性肿瘤发病与死亡情况分析</title>
  <dc:creator>&lt;strong&gt;陈琼&lt;/strong&gt;，徐慧芳，郭兰伟，康瑞华，刘茵，王潇杨，郑黎阳，张璐瑶，刘曙正，孙喜斌，张韶凯</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-08-10-2017-cancer/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="目的" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="目的">目的</h2>
<p>描述2017年河南省恶性肿瘤发病与死亡情况，为恶性肿瘤防控策略的制定提供科学依据。</p>
</section>
<section id="方法" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="方法">方法</h2>
<p>以完整性、有效性和可靠性等质量控制指标评估2017年河南省肿瘤登记数据质量，计算分城乡、性别、年龄组及部位登记人群的发病率和死亡率，结合2017年全省人口数据估算全省各部位的恶性肿瘤发病、死亡数据，计算各项统计指标。人口标准化率按照2000年中国标准人口结构（中标率）和Segi’s 世界标准人口结构（世标率）进行计算。</p>
</section>
<section id="结果" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结果">结果</h2>
<p>河南省2017年恶性肿瘤新发病例数约289862例，发病率为267.75/10万（男性为276.99/10万，女性为257.78/10万），中国人口标化率（中标率）为199.93/10万，世界人口标化率（世标率）为202.82/10万，0-74岁累积率为23.26%。城市地区发病率为269.00/10万，中标率为196.16/10万；农村地区发病率为267.22/10万，中标率为201.60/10万。河南省2017年恶性肿瘤死亡病例数约为184292例，恶性肿瘤死亡率为170.23/10万（男性为200.11/10万，女性为138.01/10万），中标率为121.24/10万，世标率为120.91/10万，0-74岁累积率为13.63%。城市地区恶性肿瘤死亡率为163.86/10万，中标死亡率为112.99/10万；农村地区死亡率为172.95/10万，中标死亡率为124.95/10万。河南最常见的恶性肿瘤为肺癌、胃癌、食管癌、肝癌和乳腺癌等，前十位发病约占全部恶性肿瘤发病的81.16%。肺癌、胃癌、肝癌、食管癌和结直肠癌等是主要的肿瘤死因，前十位死亡占全部恶性肿瘤死亡病例的86.17%。</p>
</section>
<section id="结论" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结论">结论</h2>
<p>河南省恶性肿瘤以消化系统恶性肿瘤为主，仍处于较高水平，应加大综合防控力度，以应对恶性肿瘤严峻的防控形式。</p>
<p>【关键词】 河南省；恶性肿瘤；发病；死亡；癌谱</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>中文论文</category>
  <category>第一作者</category>
  <category>肿瘤登记</category>
  <category>中华肿瘤防治</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-08-10-2017-cancer/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Incidence and mortality of colorectal cancer in 2017 and the time-trend from 2010 to 2017 in Henan province, China: a population-based registry study</title>
  <dc:creator>Jian-Gong Zhang, Yin Liu, &lt;strong&gt;Qiong Chen&lt;/strong&gt;, Hui-Fang Xu, Xiao-Yang Wang, Lan-Wei Guo, Rui-Hua Kang, Lu-Yao Zhang, Hong Wang, Shao-Kai Zhang</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-colorectal-cancer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="background" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="background">Background</h2>
<p>Henan province is an area with a serious disease burden of colorectal cancer (CRC) in China. Understanding the current incidence and mortality and the time-trend is critical to formulate and optimize prevention and control strategies for CRC. However, the current incidence and mortality and time-trend of CRC in Henan province, China have not been reported.</p>
</section>
<section id="methods" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="methods">Methods</h2>
<p>CRC data was got from the Henan Provincial Central Cancer Registry of China in which the data was submitted from local cancer registries. Combined with the census data, the incidence, mortality, proportion, age-standardized rate by Chinese population (ASRC), age-standardized rate by world population (ASRW), and cumulative incidence and mortality (0-74 years old) of CRC by urban and rural population, gender, and age groups were estimated. The average annual percentage change (AAPC) and its 95% confidence interval (CI) of ASRC from 2010 to 2017 were analyzed.</p>
</section>
<section id="results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results">Results</h2>
<p>In 2017, it was estimated that there were 20,275 new cases and 10,046 deaths of CRC in Henan province. The crude incidence was 18.73/100,000, with an age-standardized incidence rate by Chinese population (ASIRC) of 13.97/100,000 and age-standardized mortality rate by world population (ASIRW) of 13.78/100,000. The cumulative incidence was 1.66%. The mortality rate was 9.28/100,000, with an age-standardized mortality rate by Chinese population (ASMRC) of 6.49/100,000 and an age-standardized mortality rate by world population (ASMRW) of 6.45/100,000. The cumulative mortality rate was 0.69%. The ASIRC and ASMRC were higher in urban areas (15.89/100,000, 7.19/100,000) than in rural areas (13.13/100,000, 6.20/100,000), and higher in males (15.53/100,000, 7.44/100,000) than in females (12.48/100,000, 5.66/100,000). The age-specific incidence reached the peak at age of 80-84, and the age-specific mortality reached the peak at age 85. From 2010 to 2017, the overall ASIRC and ASMRC showed a steady trend (P&gt;0.05), while an upward trend was observed in the mortality rate in urban males (AAPC =3.4, 95% CI: 0.2-6.7, P=0.040).</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>The incidence and mortality of CRC were high in Henan province, and higher in urban areas and males. It is critical to strengthen the prevention and control of CRC, carry out targeted intervention, and promote screening and early diagnosis and treatment, particularly among urban areas and males.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords</strong>: China; Colorectal cancer (CRC); incidence; mortality; trend.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>英文论文</category>
  <category>共同作者</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-colorectal-cancer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Time-trend of the incidence and mortality of esophageal cancer from 2010 to 2018 and its statistics in 2018 in Henan, China</title>
  <dc:creator>Jian-Gong Zhang, Hui-Fang Xu, &lt;strong&gt;Qiong Chen&lt;/strong&gt;, Lu-Yao Zhang, Xiao-Yang Wang, Hong Wang, Yin Liu, Shu-Zheng Liu, Lan-Wei Guo, Li-Yang Zheng, Yi-Xian Wang, Yi-Ping Jing, Chun-Ya Liu, You-Lin Qiao, Shao-Kai Zhang, Bin-Bin Han</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-esophagus-cancer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="background" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="background">Background</h2>
<p>It is great of significance to figure the time-trend of esophageal cancer (EC) and its current status for effective prevention and control, especially in EC high risk areas. As one of world-renowned high-risk areas, the epidemiology of EC in Henan has not been recently updated. Therefore, we aimed to depict the status quo of EC and analyze its time-trend in Henan.</p>
</section>
<section id="methods" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="methods">Methods</h2>
<p>The EC data were extracted from the Henan Provincial Cancer registry database derived from the population based cancer registry system, which covered 30.51% of the whole population in Henan and were qualified according to national and international guidelines. The incidence and mortality of EC were estimated by area (rural/urban), gender, and age groups. The age-standardized rates (ASRs) were calculated according to the Segi’s population. Joinpoint regression was used to calculate annual percentage change (APC) and average annual percentage change (AAPC) to evaluate the time-trend of EC.</p>
</section>
<section id="results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results">Results</h2>
<p>As estimated, there were 29,913 new EC cases in Henan, 2018. The crude incidence and the age-standardized incidence rate by world standard population (ASIRW) was 27.43/105 and 19.96/105, respectively. The incidence in males and rural was 1.83 and 1.51 times higher than that in females and urban areas, respectively. Meanwhile, it was estimated that 22,688 deaths occurred in 2018. The crude mortality and the age-standardized mortality rate by world standard population (ASMRW) were 20.80/105 and 14.47/105, respectively. Similarly, males and rural areas had higher mortality compared with females and urban areas. The age-specific incidence and mortality of EC showed significant increasing after 60-64 years group. In general, the time-trend of incidence (APC: -8.9, P&lt;0.001) and mortality (APC: -7.6, P&lt;0.001) of EC showed a significant decreasing trend since 2014, and downward trend were also observed in rural areas for incidence (APC: -5.2, P&lt;0.001) and mortality (APC: -3.9, P&lt;0.001) from 2010 to 2018.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>The EC incidence and mortality in Henan has exhibited a significant declining trend in past years. Nonetheless, the disease burden remains high, especially in males and rural areas. Therefore, the ongoing prevention and control strategies of EC should be maintained alongside the establishment of more effective strategies.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords</strong>: Esophageal cancer (EC); Henan; incidence; mortality; trend.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>英文论文</category>
  <category>共同作者</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-esophagus-cancer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>亚太结直肠癌风险评分系统在我国北方无症状人群筛查中的应用</title>
  <dc:creator>郭兰伟, 郑黎阳, &lt;strong&gt;陈琼&lt;/strong&gt;, 刘茵, 徐慧芳, 康瑞华, 张璐瑶, 刘曙正, 孙喜斌, 张韶凯</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-07-26-risk-score.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="目的" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="目的">目的</h2>
<p>评价亚太结直肠癌筛查评分系统（APCS）在我国北方无症状人群筛查中的应用价值。</p>
</section>
<section id="方法" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="方法">方法</h2>
<p>采取整群抽样的方法，选取河南省40～74岁城市户籍无症状人群进行癌症危险因素调查和结肠镜检查，应用APCS计算每位研究对象患进展期肿瘤的危险分值，绘制受试者工作特征（ROC）曲线，并计算曲线下面积（AUC）和95%可信区间（95%CI)，并采用Logistic回归分析计算不同危险分层中患结直肠进展期肿瘤的OR值及95%CI。</p>
</section>
<section id="结果" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结果">结果</h2>
<p>共纳入无症状人群7 454例，接受结肠镜检查前评分，平均年龄（55.01±7.91）岁，进展期肿瘤检出率为1.50%。APCS分值范围为0～7分，预测的一致性好（P=0.886），区分能力一般（AUC为0.628,95%CI:0.579～0.678），但优于仅基于年龄变量的预测模型。以低风险组（0～1分）为对照组，中风险组（2～3分）和高风险组（4～7分）发生进展期肿瘤的风险分别为低风险组的1.97倍（95%CI:0.83～4.65）和4.07倍（95%CI:1.76～9.42）。</p>
</section>
<section id="结论" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结论">结论</h2>
<p>基于年龄、性别、一级亲属结直肠癌家族史和吸烟构建的APCS是确定中国北方无症状人群进展期肿瘤风险的有用工具。</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>中文论文</category>
  <category>共同作者</category>
  <category>中国肿瘤</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-07-26-risk-score.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>河南省2016年肝癌的发病与死亡情况及2010-2016年趋势分析</title>
  <dc:creator>&lt;strong&gt;陈琼&lt;/strong&gt;，刘茵，刘曙正，郭兰伟，郑黎阳，徐慧芳，王潇杨，王红，孙喜斌，张韶凯</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-06-30-liver.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="目的" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="目的">目的</h2>
<p>根据河南省肿瘤登记地区肿瘤登记数据估算河南省2016年肝癌发病与死亡情况。</p>
</section>
<section id="方法" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="方法">方法</h2>
<p>按照《中国肿瘤登记手册》及国际癌症研究中心的登记质量标准评估2016年河南省肿瘤登记数据的完整性、有效性和可靠性。按照ICD10编码（C22）提取肝癌数据，并分别计算城乡、性别、年龄别登记人群肝癌发病率和死亡率，结合2016年全省人口数据估算全省肝癌发病及死亡情况。采用2000年中国标准人口年龄构成和Segi世界标准人口年龄构成分别计算中国人口标化率（简称中标率）、世界人口标化率（简称世标率）。采用Joinpoint回归模型估计肝癌中标发病率和中标死亡率年度变化百分比（annual percent change,APC）。</p>
</section>
<section id="结果" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结果">结果</h2>
<p>河南省2016年肝癌新发病例数为28 635例，占河南省全部恶性肿瘤新发病例的9.58%，位居全部恶性肿瘤发病的第4位。肝癌粗发病率为26.43/10万，中标率为19.90/10万，世标发病率为19.79/10万；男性发病率高于女性，男性和女性中标发病率分别为28.07/10万和11.76/10万；农村地区发病率高于城市地区，中标发病率分别为20.50/10万和17.84/10万。河南省2016年肝癌死亡病例数为24 052例，占河南省全部恶性肿瘤死亡的12.82%，位居全部恶性肿瘤死亡的第4位。肝癌粗死亡率为22.22/10万，中标死亡率为16.30/10万，世标死亡率为16.27/10万；男性死亡率高于女性，中标死亡率分别为22.99/10万和9.77/10万；城市地区和农村地区差别不大，肝癌中标死亡率分别为16.08/10万和16.41/10万。肝癌的年龄别发病率和死亡率在0～29岁年龄组和0～34岁年龄组较低，分别在30岁以后和35岁以后快速上升，均在85+岁年龄组达到峰值；肝癌新发病例数和估计死亡人数均在60～64岁年龄组达到峰值。2010年以来肝癌中标发病率平均每年下降2.1%。2013年以来肝癌中标死亡率平均每年下降7.4%。</p>
</section>
<section id="结论" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结论">结论</h2>
<p>河南省肝癌疾病负担较重，其城乡及男女性别差异明显，因此，应针对其流行特点及危险因素加大综合防控力度。</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>中文论文</category>
  <category>第一作者</category>
  <category>肿瘤登记</category>
  <category>肝癌电子杂志</category>
  <category>肝癌</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-06-30-liver.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>河南省2017年胃癌发病及死亡与2010-2017年流行趋势分析</title>
  <dc:creator>张韶凯, &lt;strong&gt;陈琼&lt;/strong&gt;, 徐慧芳, 刘茵, 刘曙正, 郭兰伟, 郑黎阳, 康瑞华, 张建功</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-06-14-gastric-cancer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="目的" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="目的">目的</h2>
<p>估计河南省2017年胃癌的发病及死亡情况，并分析2010-2017年河南省胃癌的流行变化趋势。评价亚太结直肠癌筛查评分系统（APCS）在我国北方无症状人群筛查中的应用价值</p>
</section>
<section id="方法" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="方法">方法</h2>
<p>本研究数据均来自于河南省内38个肿瘤登记处上报的2017年恶性肿瘤登记数据，所有数据均按照《中国肿瘤登记手册》以及国际癌症研究署的肿瘤登记数据质量标准进行数据完整性、有效性和可靠性评估。根据符合质量要求的数据及2017年河南省的户籍人口数据，分别按照城乡和年龄分层，估计2017年河南省胃癌的发病及死亡情况。根据2010-2017年河南省胃癌的中标发病率和中标死亡率数据，分析河南省胃癌的流行趋势变化。采取整群抽样的方法，选取河南省40～74岁城市户籍无症状人群进行癌症危险因素调查和结肠镜检查，应用APCS计算每位研究对象患进展期肿瘤的危险分值，绘制受试者工作特征（ROC）曲线，并计算曲线下面积（AUC）和95%可信区间（95%CI)，并采用Logistic回归分析计算不同危险分层中患结直肠进展期肿瘤的OR值及95%CI。</p>
</section>
<section id="结果" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结果">结果</h2>
<p>2017年河南省估计有39 101例新发胃癌，30 732例死亡。河南省胃癌发病率为36.12/10万，中标发病率为26.39/10万，0～74岁累积发病率为3.3%,男性中标发病率是女性的2.54倍。城市和农村地区的胃癌中标发病率分别为23.37/10万和27.73/10万。河南省2017年胃癌死亡率为28.39/10万，中标死亡率为19.9/10万，0～74岁累积死亡率为2.32%,男性中标死亡率是女性的2.60倍。城市和农村地区的胃癌中标死亡率分别为17.02/10万和21.17/10万。2010-2017年河南省胃癌发病率(APC=-2.4%,P&lt;0.05)及2012-2017年胃癌死亡率(APC=-2.4%,P&lt;0.05)呈稳定下降趋势。共纳入无症状人群7 454例，接受结肠镜检查前评分，平均年龄（55.01±7.91）岁，进展期肿瘤检出率为1.50%。APCS分值范围为0～7分，预测的一致性好（P=0.886），区分能力一般（AUC为0.628,95%CI:0.579～0.678），但优于仅基于年龄变量的预测模型。以低风险组（0～1分）为对照组，中风险组（2～3分）和高风险组（4～7分）发生进展期肿瘤的风险分别为低风险组的1.97倍（95%CI:0.83～4.65）和4.07倍（95%CI:1.76～9.42）</p>
</section>
<section id="结论" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结论">结论</h2>
<p>尽管河南省胃癌的发病率和死亡率在2010-2017年呈现稳定下降趋势，但2017年河南省的胃癌流行形势依然严峻，应继续开展有效的防控措施，降低胃癌的发病率及死亡率，减轻胃癌的发病及死亡。基于年龄、性别、一级亲属结直肠癌家族史和吸烟构建的APCS是确定中国北方无症状人群进展期肿瘤风险的有用工具。</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>中文论文</category>
  <category>共同作者</category>
  <category>中华肿瘤防治杂志</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-06-14-gastric-cancer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Special issue (The advance of solid tumor research in China): Participants with a family history of cancer have a higher participation rate in low-dose computed tomography for lung cancer screening</title>
  <dc:creator>Lan-Wei Guo, Qing-Cheng Meng, Li-Yang Zheng, &lt;strong&gt;Qiong Chen&lt;/strong&gt;, Yin Liu, Hui-Fang Xu, Rui-Hua Kang, Lu-Yao Zhang, Shu-Zheng Liu, Xi-Bin Sun, Shao-Kai Zhang</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-Solid-tumor-research.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>We aimed to determine participation in low-dose computed tomography (LDCT) of individuals with a family history of common cancers in a population-based screening program to provide timely evidence in high-risk populations in China. The analysis was conducted using data from the Cancer Screening Program in Urban China (CanSPUC), which recruited 282 377 participants aged 40 to 74 years from eight cities in the Henan province. Using the CanSPUC risk score system, 55 428 participants were evaluated to have high risk for lung cancer and were recommended for LDCT. We calculated the overall and group-specific participation rates using family history of common cancers and compared differences in participation rates between different groups. Odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals were derived by multivariable logistic regression. Of the 55 428 participants, 22 260 underwent LDCT (participation rate, 40.16%). Family history of lung, esophageal, stomach, liver and colorectal cancer was associated with increased participation in LDCT screening. The odds of participants with a family history of one, two, three and four or more cancer cases undergoing LDCT screening were 1.9, 2.7, 2.8 and 3.5 times, respectively, than those without a family history of cancer. Compared to those without a history of cancer, participation in LDCT gradually increased as the number of cancer cases in the family increased (P &lt; .001). Our findings suggest that there is room for improvement in lung cancer screening given the relatively low participation rate. Lung cancer screening in populations with a family history of cancer may improve efficiency and cost-effectiveness; however, this requires further verification.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords: </strong>adherence; early detection; family history; low-dose computed tomography; lung cancer.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>英文论文</category>
  <category>共同作者</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-Solid-tumor-research.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2021河南省肿瘤登记年报</title>
  <dc:creator>张建功，张韶凯， &lt;strong&gt;陈琼&lt;/strong&gt;</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/books/2021-annual report.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><img src="https://chenq.site/publications/books/cover/2021.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>肿瘤登记年报</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/books/2021-annual report.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://chenq.site/publications/books/cover/2021.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>基线细胞学正常女性高危型人乳头瘤病毒感染与宫颈病变发病风险的3年随访研究</title>
  <dc:creator>郭珍，赵冬梅，贾漫漫，陈琼，陈红敏，任玲艳，陈佩佩，孙星媛，李梦洁，孙喜斌，张韶凯</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-03-15-HPV.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="目的" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="目的">[目的]</h2>
<p>探讨基线细胞学正常妇女在3年随访过程中感染高危型人乳头瘤病毒（HR-HPV）及发生宫颈病变的情况。</p>
</section>
<section id="方法" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="方法">[方法]</h2>
<p>选择2017年4月至5月在河南省济源市宫颈癌筛查中细胞学结果正常的3 555名妇女为研究对象。对所有研究对象随访3年，HR-HPV阳性者每年随访1次，HR-HPV阴性者第3年随访1次。随访中以病理诊断结果为宫颈上皮内瘤变2级及以上（CIN2+）为终点，分析HPV感染变化和CIN2+的发病风险。</p>
</section>
<section id="结果" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结果">[结果]</h2>
<p>（1）HR-HPV阴性者：共2 455名基线细胞学正常且HR-HPV阴性妇女在第3年成功随访，HR-HPV新发阳性率为13.08%（321/2 455），其中HPV 16、18、33、52和58型别的新发阳性率分别为2.00%、0.94%、0.90%、3.50%、1.71%；年龄＜45岁者HR-HPV、HPV 16、HPV 52新发阳性率均低于≥45岁者（10.7%vs 14.6%、0.9%vs 2.7%、2.2%vs 4.3%），差异均具有统计学意义（P均＜0.05）。细胞学结果为意义不明的不典型鳞状细胞及以上者63例，8例被诊断为CIN1,3例被诊断CIN2，病变进展率为0.45%。（2）HR-HPV阳性者：共573名基线细胞学正常而HR-HPV阳性妇女需要随访，3次随访时HR-HPV转阴率分别为29.68%、39.06%、46.80%,CIN2+检出率分别为2.59%、2.58%、2.43%,3年CIN2+累计发生率为7.53%。年龄＜45岁者3次随访HR-HPV转阴率均高于≥45岁者（35.5%vs26.8%、51.0%vs 33.1%、58.6%vs 40.5%），差异均有统计学意义（P均＜0.05）。</p>
</section>
<section id="结论" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结论">[结论]</h2>
<p>宫颈癌筛查人群中细胞学正常且HR-HPV阴性妇女，其3年后随访时HR-HPV新发阳性率和CIN2+的发生风险均较低。细胞学正常而HR-HPV阳性妇女中，≥45岁者不仅清除既往HR-HPV感染的能力减弱，且更易出现新发感染或多种型别共感染现象，发生CIN2+的风险也较高。因此，可以适当延长基线细胞学正常且HRHPV阴性妇女的随访时间间隔，对围绝经期女性人群应加强随访监测。</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>中文论文</category>
  <category>共同作者</category>
  <category>癌症筛查</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-03-15-HPV.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2010-2016年食管癌发病与死亡情况趋势分析</title>
  <dc:creator>&lt;strong&gt;陈琼&lt;/strong&gt;, 徐慧芳，刘曙正, 郭兰伟，曹小琴，郑黎阳，孙喜斌, 张韶凯</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-02-24-esophagus/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="cell" data-hash="index_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-1_8084660ecc537b9e63600028840c6b05">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<p><img src="https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-02-24-esophagus/image/cover.png" class="img-fluid" width="278"></p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="目的" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="目的">目的</h2>
<p>根据河南省肿瘤登记数据估算河南省2016年食管癌发病和死亡情况，分析2010—2016年食管癌发病和死亡变化趋势。</p>
</section>
<section id="方法" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="方法">方法</h2>
<p>按照《中国肿瘤登记手册》以及国际癌症研究中心的登记质量标准评估2016年河南省肿瘤登记数据的完整性、有效性和可靠性，按照国际疾病分类10编码（C15）提取食管癌数据，并分城乡、性别、年龄组计算登记人群食管癌发病率和死亡率，结合2016年全省人口数据估算全省食管癌发病、死亡情况。人口标准化率按照2000年中国标准人口结构（中标率）和Segi’s 世界标准人口结构（世标率）进行计算。采用Joinpoint模型估计食管癌中标发病率和中标死亡率年度变化百分比（APC）。</p>
</section>
<section id="结果" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结果">结果</h2>
<p>2016年河南省食管癌新发病例数为4.01万例，占河南省全部恶性肿瘤新发病例的13.46%，位于全部恶性肿瘤发病的第3位。食管癌粗发病率为37.21/10万，中标率为26.74/10万，世标率为27.12/10万；男性发病率高于女性，男性和女性中标发病率分别为34.53/10万和19.19/10万；农村地区发病率高于城市地区，中标率分别为28.13/10万和20.90/10万。河南省2016年食管癌死亡病例数为2.93万例，占河南省全部恶性肿瘤死亡的15.61%，位于全部恶性肿瘤死亡的第3位。食管癌粗死亡率为27.14/10万，中标率为18.74/10万，世标率为18.78/10万；男性死亡率高于女性，中标率分别为24.78/10万和13.12/10万；农村地区高于城市地区，食管癌中标死亡率分别为19.48/10万和15.73/10万。2010—2016年间，河南省食管癌中标发病率（APC=-3.12%, 95%CI:-5.30~ -0.90, P=0.01）和中标死亡率（APC=-2.47%, 95CI:-4.70~ -0.20, P=0.04）平均每年分别下降3.12%和2.47%；不同地区变化趋势不同，农村地区中标发病率和死亡率均呈现下降趋势，而城市地区变化趋势无统计学意义；男性和女性中标发病率和死亡率变化趋势相同，均呈现下降趋势。</p>
</section>
<section id="结论" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="结论">结论</h2>
<p>近年来河南省食管癌发病和死亡呈下降趋势，但是其疾病负担仍然较重，农村地区为食管癌高发区，应坚持“以预防为主”和“以农村为重点”的原则，开展食管癌防控工作。</p>
【<strong>关键词</strong>】食管肿瘤；发病；死亡；河南省
<hr>
</section>
<section id="主要结果图" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="主要结果图">主要结果图</h2>
<div class="cell" data-hash="index_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-2_1deb69d6d8604424c455a7815172522c">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-02-24-esophagus/image/trend.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="1500"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">2010-2016年河南省食管癌发病率死亡率时间变化趋势.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>中文论文</category>
  <category>第一作者</category>
  <category>肿瘤登记</category>
  <category>食管癌</category>
  <category>中华肿瘤杂志</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/firstauthor/2022-02-24-esophagus/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Risk of liver cirrhosis in HBV/HCV infected individuals with First-degree relatives who have liver cancer: development and validation of a simple model</title>
  <dc:creator>Yin Liu, Lan-Wei Guo, Hui-Fang Xu, Rui-Hua Kang, Li-Yang Zheng, Lu-Yao Zhang, &lt;strong&gt;Qiong Chen&lt;/strong&gt;, Xi-Bin Sun, Shao-Kai Zhang, You-Lin Qiao</dc:creator>
  <link>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-HBV-Liver-cancer.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Identification of high-risk population among hepatitis B virus (HBV)/hepatitis C virus (HCV)-infected individuals with first-degree relatives (FDR) who have liver cancer is important to implement precise intervention. A cross-sectional study was conducted under the framework of a population-based Cancer Screening Program in Urban China (CanSPUC), aimed to develop and validate a simple noninvasive model that could assess and stratify cirrhosis risk, in HBV/HCV-infected individuals with FDRs who have liver cancer. People who participated in liver cancer screening in Henan province were enrolled. Using the data set consisting of participants admitted from October 1, 2013, to December 31, 2016, a 24-point scale risk score model was developed through logistic regression, based on educational background, dietary habit, smoking index, cooking oil fume exposure, history of severe trauma, HBV/HCV infection status, history of diabetes, history of hyperlipidemia, and parent history of liver cancer. The model showed excellent discrimination with area under the receiver operator characteristic curve (AUROC) of 0.875 [95% confidence interval (CI), 0.853-0.896] and fair calibration with a Hosmer-Lemeshow test P = 0.106. The prevalence rates in the medium- and high-risk groups were 2.87 (95% CI, 1.94-4.25) and 47.57 (95% CI, 31.59-71.63) times of low-risk group, respectively. After internal validation, bias-corrected AUROC was 0.874 (95% CI, 0.873-0.875). In the external validation data set consisting of participants admitted from January 1, 2017, to October 31, 2018, the model had achieved similar discrimination, calibration, and risk stratification ability. In conclusion, the risk score model we developed can be a practical tool for the screening and prevention of liver cirrhosis among HBV/HCV-infected individuals with FDRs who have liver cancer. PREVENTION RELEVANCE: We created a simple and noninvasive cirrhosis risk model for individuals infected by HBV/HCV who have FDRs with liver cancer. This model is useful not only for the prognosis of HBV/HCV infection, but also for the prevention of hepatocellular carcinoma.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>英文论文</category>
  <category>共同作者</category>
  <guid>https://chenq.site/publications/coauthor/2022-HBV-Liver-cancer.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
